Dr. Parag Jyoti Bezbaruah, PhD., M.Tech., B.Tech.

Senior Faculty-OCFP, Orchids The International School

Current CTC: 7.5 Lakhs Per annum

E-mail: <u>bezbaruahparag@gmail.com</u>

Contact No: +91-9436316115/+91-8638278880

Orcid: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7591-6791

ResearchGate: https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Parag-Bezbaruah-2



Profile:

A highly motivated and an enthusiastic doctorate seeking exposure to a progressive and an esteemed institution, which will provide me an opportunity to apply my knowledge and skills and will keep me abreast with latest trends and technologies. I am a central university gold medallist in M.Tech and a doctorate from Mechanical Engineering Department, National Institute of Technology Meghalaya. My research work was based on developing a highly efficient solar air collector to abate the electricity consumption by minimizing the heat load requirement for space heating. The structure was modelled and simulated using ANSYS FLUENT and was validated experimentally. The work was published in some renowned journals like Renewable Energy, Heat and Mass Transfer, Solar Energy etc. Along with a doctorate degree, I also have an industrial experience of 1.5+ years and a teaching experience for a semester as an Assistant Professor in Swami Keshvanand Institute of Technology, Jaipur. Right now, I am working as a Senior faculty-OCFP in Orchids The International School, Bengaluru.

Subject of Interest:

- Solar thermal applications
- Computational fluid dynamics
- Renewable energy
- Heat transfer
- Energy management and audit
- Refrigeration and Air conditioning
- Thermal Engineering
- Optimisation Techniques
- Fluid mechanics

Professional Experience:

EXPERINCE (2+YEAR)

- Senior faculty- OCPF at Orchids the International School from 7th February till date.
- As an Assistant Professor at Swami Keshvanand Institute of Technology, Jaipur from 27th September 2021 to 12th January 2022.
- Guest Faculty at North East Hill University, Meghalaya from 1st October 2015 to 9thJanuary 2016 (4 months).
- As a JRF in Tezpur University, Assam, from 24 June to 24 September 2015 (4 months).
- As a JRF in Madras School of Economics, Chennai from 1st June to 30th June 2015 (1 month).
- Project & Maintenance Engineer at R. K. Marble Pvt Ltd., Ajmer from 9th December 2010 to 26th May 2012 (18 months).

Computer skills:

- Completed a short term course on AutoCAD, Pro-E Wildfire 4.0 and Catia V5 R19.0 from CIPET, Jaipur.
- A certified course on Microsoft Office.
- ANSYS FLUENT.

Educational Background:

Examination	Board/University	Year of passing	Percentage/CGPA and Achievements
Doctor of Philosophy in Mechanical Engineering.	National Institute of Technology Meghalaya	2021	9.00
Master of Technology in Energy Technology	Tezpur University	2015	9.33 (Gold Medallist)
Bachelor of Technology in Mechanical Engineering	Rajasthan Technical University	2010	68% (Institute academic winner)
HS (12 th)	CBSE	2006	76.2%
HSLC (10 th)	CBSE	2004	83%

Academic Achievements and Accolades:

- Recipient of "International Travel Support" funded by SERB-DST, Govt. of India to attend the 14th International Conference on Heat Transfer, Fluid mechanics and Thermodynamics (HEFAT 2019) in Ireland.
- Best paper presentation award in ICRIDME 2019 organized by NIT Meghalaya.
- Best presentation award in ICAER 2017 organized by IIT Bombay.
- University Gold Medallist award for the academic year 2013-2015 from Tezpur Central University.
- Qualified "Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE) 2013" in Mechanical Engineering
- Academic Excellence Award for securing the second rank in B.Tech third year and first rank in B.Tech final year.

Training & Workshops:

- Participated in the five-day Faculty Development Programme on "Robotics and Mechatronics in Manufacturing" held from 15th November to 19th November at Swami Keshvanand Institute of Technology, Management & Gramothan, Jaipur.
- Successfully completed AICTE Training And Learning (ATAL) Academy Online Elementary FDP on "3D Printing Basics and Applications" from 25th to 29th October 2021 at MBM Engineering College Jodhpur.
- Successfully completed AICTE Training And Learning (ATAL) Academy Online Elementary FDP on "Artificial Intelligence in the Renewable Power Generation" from 18th to 22nd October 2021 at University of Lucknow.
- Successfully completed the 4-day training webinar on TRNSYS produced by Thermal Energy System Specialists on April 26th through April 29th 2021.

- Participated in the conclave on "Transforming Meghalaya State through Science & Technology Interventions" organised by North East Centre for Technology Application and Reach (NECTAR) on April 9th-10th 2021.
- Attended a short-term course under TEQIP-III on "Advances in Energy Storage Technology" held from 9th March to 13th March 2020 at IIT Delhi.
- Participated in a workshop under TEQIP-III on "Hands in Training on ANSYS for Computational Fluid Dynamics" held from 6th September to 10th September 2019 at NIT Meghalaya.
- Participated in a workshop on "Engineering Design and Simulation" organized by NIT Meghalaya and ELMAX on 7th March 2018.
- Attended a "Solar Awareness Training Programme on Off Grid Solar Energy Technologies" sponsored by MNRE and conducted by National Power Training Institute from 20th Feb to 22th Feb 2017.
- Participated in a workshop on "Advances in Applications of Computational Fluid Dynamics" held from 7th November to 11th November 2019 at NIT Silchar.
- Successfully completed training on "Functioning and Maintenance of Solar Radiation Resource Assessment Station" organized by CWET, Chennai on 3rd-4th July 2014.
- Participated in a Indo-Finnish workshop on "Green Chemistry" held from 13th December to 14th December 2013 at Tezpur University.
- B. Tech 6th semester Industrial training from "Bongaigaon Refinery (IOCL)" for a period of 30 days from 29/05/2009 to 30/06/2009.
- B.Tech 4th semester Industrial training from "Bongaigaon Refinery Petrochemical Limited" for a period of 30 days from 16/06/2008 to 16/07/2008.

Research Highlights:

A. Reviewer of the following journals

- Hear and Mass Transfer [Springer]
- Applied Solar Energy [Springer]
- International Journal of Heat and Mass Transfer [Elsevier]
- Journal of Thermal Science and Engineering Applications [ASME]
- Solar Energy [Elsevier]
- Renewable Energy [Elsevier]

B. List of Publications

Journal Papers

- 1. **Bezbaruah, P.J.**, Das, R.S. & Sarkar, B.K., "Experimental and numerical analysis of solar air heater accountered with modified conical vortex generators in a staggered fashion," *Renewable Energy*, vol. 180, pp. 109-131, 2021. (SCI, IF: 8.001)
- 2. **Bezbaruah, P.J.**, Das, R.S. & Sarkar, B.K., "Experimentally validated 3D simulation and performance optimization of a solar air duct with modified conical vortex generators," *Solar Energy*, vol. 224, pp. 1040-1062, 2021. **(SCI, IF: 5.742)**

- 3. **Bezbaruah, P.J.**, Das, R.S. & Sarkar, B.K., "Overall performance analysis and GRA optimization of solar air heater with truncated half conical vortex generators," *Solar Energy*, vol. 196(15), pp. 637-652, 2020. (SCI, IF: 5.742)
- 4. **Bezbaruah**, **P.J.**, Borah, D. & Baruah, D.C., "An Experimental Investigation to Check the Overall Performance of a Packed Bed Solar Air Heater", *Applied Solar Energy*, vol. 56(6), pp. 431-441, 2020. (SCOPUS)
- 5. **Bezbaruah, P.J.**, Das, R.S. & Sarkar, B.K., "Solar air heater with finned absorber plate and helical flow path: A CFD analysis," *Applied Solar Energy*, vol. 56(1), pp. 35-41, 2020. **(SCOPUS)**
- 6. **Bezbaruah, P.J.**, Das, R.S. & Sarkar, B.K., "Thermo-hydraulic performance augmentation of solar air duct using modified forms of conical vortex generators," *Heat Mass Transfer*, vol. 55, pp. 1387-1403, 2019. **(SCI, IF: 2.464)**
- 7. **Bezbaruah, P.J.**, Das, R.S. & Sarkar, B.K., "Thermal and fluid flow dynamics of miller teeth shaped ribbed solar air heater-A CFD analysis," *Journal of Scientific and Industrial Research*, vol. 78(10), pp. 694-698, 2019. **(SCI, IF: 1.056)**

❖ Book Chapters

- 1. **Bezbaruah, P.J.**, Das, A., Das, R.S. & Sarkar, B.K., "Numerical investigation on triangular fin based solar air heater," In: Singh S., Ramadesigan V. (eds) *Advances in Energy Research, Vol. 2.* Springer, Singapore, pp. 341-351, 2020.
- 2. **Bezbaruah, P.J.**, Patowary, R., Borah, D. & Baruah, D.C., "Thermohydraulic performance of packed bed solar air heater," In: Singh S., Ramadesigan V. (eds) *Advances in Energy Research, Vol. 2.* Springer, Singapore, pp. 323-339, 2020.
- 3. **Bezbaruah P.J.**, Das R.S., Sarkar B.K., "CFD-Based Study on Thermal and Fluid Flow Dynamics Due to Miller Teeth Shaped Ribs Over Absorber Plate of Solar Air Collector," In: Biswal B., Sarkar B., Mahanta P. (eds) *Advances in Mechanical Engineering. Lecture Notes in Mechanical Engineering*, Springer, Singapore, pp. 1045-1053.

Conference Papers

- 1. Bhandarkar A.C., **Bezbaruah P.J.**, Sarkar B.K., Das R.S., "Solar air heater system control for space heating application in Shillong"8th International and 47th National Conference on Fluid Mechanics and Fluid Power (FMFP), IIT Guwahati. Paper ID: 154"
- 2. **Bezbaruah P.J.,** Gupta A.K., Das R.S., Sarkar B.K., "CFD analysis of solar collector with truncated hemispherical vortex generators" *Proceedings of 14th International Conference on Heat Transfer, Fluid Mechanics and Thermodynamics (HEFAT 2019)*, pp. 265-270. Paper ID: 348, July 21-24, 2019, **Wicklow, Ireland.**
- 3. **Bezbaruah P.J.**, Kumar R., Das R.S., "Thermohydraulic performance analysis of solar air heater with helical roughness," *Proceedings of the 25th National and 3rd International ISHMT-ASTFE Heat and Mass Transfer conference (IHMTC-2019)*, pp. 233-237, 2019
- 4. **Bezbaruah P.J.**, Das R.S., Sarkar B.K., "Numerical Analysis of Solar Triangular Air Duct with Conical Turbulators," *2nd International Conference on Power, Energy and Environment: Towards Smart Technology (ICEPE)*, Shillong, India, pp. 1-5, 2018.
- 5. Gupta A.K., **Bezbaruah P.J.**, Das R.S., Sarkar B.K., "Numerical Investigation on Solar Air Heater with Hemispherical Roughness," *2nd International Conference on Power, Energy and Environment: Towards Smart Technology (ICEPE)*, Shillong, India, pp. 1-6, 2018.

Projects:

- PhD project entitled "Studies of the Thermohydraulic Performance of Solar Air Heater with Novel Vortex Generators".
- State Council of Science, Technology & Environment Meghalaya sanctioned Rs. 97,834/-for the project entitled "Solar Based Room Heater Cum Food Drier with Energy Storage Unit".
- M.Tech major project on "Thermohydraulic Performance of Packed Bed Solar Air Heater".
- B.Tech major project on "Integration of CHP (Combined Heat & Power) and Building Simulation for Predicting the Energy Requirement of a Residential Building" as part of the University curriculum.

Personal information:

Nationality : IndianMarital Status : Married

Date of Birth : March 6, 1988

■ Sex : Male

Present address: Bengaluru, Karnataka

Declaration:

I hereby declare that the information given above is true to the best of my knowledge. I will make it my earnest endeavour to discharge competently and carefully the duties, you may be pleased to entrust with me.

Referees:

Name	Designation	Address	Contact Details
Dr. Debendra C Baruah	Professor	Tezpur	+91-9435508563
		University	baruahd@tezu.ernet.in
Dr. Rajat Subhra Das	Asst. Professor	NIT Meghalaya	+91-9402102380
			rajatsubhra@nitm.ac.in
Dr. Bikash Sarkar	Asst. Professor	NIT Meghalaya	+91-9485177038
			bikash.sarkar@nitm.ac.in
Dr. Dheeraj Joshi	Professor	SKIT, Jaipur	+91-9460355422
			hodme@skit.ac.in

Date: 08-02-2022 Place: Bengaluru

Signature of Candidate